Guide to the William Hesketh Leverhulme Solomon Islands photograph album, circa 1906-1910
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Hesketh Leverhulme Solomon Islands photograph album circa 1906-1910
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leverhulme, William Hesketh Lever, Viscount, 1851-1925.
0.5 linear feet Extent: 1 Volume
William Hesketh Lever was the First Viscount Leverhulme, and founder of the international firm, Lever Brothers. This bound photograph album belonging to Lord Leverhulme is entitled Solomon Islands Views, and contains 98 black-and-white photographs, chiefly measuring 6x8 inches, that illustrate the beginnings of the Lever Brothers Pacific plantations operations from about 1906-1910. Images include company buildings, plantations at various stages of development, local inhabitants and dwellings, other cultivated crops, flora and fauna, and steamships. Among the place names listed are Rendova, Pepesala and Guadalcanal. Notable persons found among the images include the Resident Commissioner of the Islands at the time, missionary J.F. Goldie, and various Lever officers.
RL.00836
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Hesketh Leverhulme Solomon Islands photograph album was acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at an unknown date.
Biographical Note
William Hesketh Lever, First Viscount Leverhulme (1851-1925), British soap manufacturer, was the founder of the well-known firm of Lever Brothers whose operations became international during his lifetime. One of Lever Brothers' major international investments was in the Solomon Islands. In 1905 the company sent Joseph Meek, chairman of Lever Brothers Australian Company, to Lever, prospect through the Pacific islands and the Straits Settlements. They selected the Solomon Islands and eventually acquired 300,000 acres. The company began coconut planting on a considerable scale, forming for this purpose an associated company called Levers' Pacific Plantations, Ltd.
Collection Overview
This handsomely bound photograph album belonging to Lord Leverhulme is entitled Solomon Islands Views, and contains 98 black-and-white photographs that illustrate the beginnings of the Lever Brothers Pacific plantations operations. Images include buildings, plantations at various stages of development, local inhabitants, and steamships. Among the place names listed are Rendova, Pepesala and Guadalcanal. Persons whose photographic portraits are found among the images are the Resident Commissioner of the Islands, missionary J.F. Goldie, and various Lever officers. The photographs illustrate the beginnings of the Lever Brothers' Pacific Plantations operations in the Solomon Islands. The views include buildings and other installations, coconut plantations in various stages of development, lumbering, native housing, local populace, local workers in various tasks, local and inter-island shipping, colonial and company officials, local chiefs, company and government headquarters, ocean steamships, steam powered agricultural equipment, copra, local flora and fauna, and the cultivation of peanuts, rubber, and sweet potatoes.
Place names listed for the photographs are: Rendova, West Bay, Erickson's Island, Pepesala, Guadalcanal, KayIan, Ufa, Banika, Tulagi, Gavatu, Lunga, Kokoon, Pampa, Kaukau, Aola, and Stanmore River. Persons in the photographs include: Charles Morris Woodford, Resident Commissioner of the Islands, 1896 to 1914, and Mrs. Woodford; Mrs. Tillotson, wife of Lord Leverhulme's nephew, John Lever Tillotson (d. 1915) who was his senior colleague on the board; Fred Wernham, an expert in tropical plantation work who was closely identified with developments in the Solomon Islands; Joseph Meek, who first journeyed to the Islands in 1905 to assess prospects there; Methodist missionary J. F. Goldie, translator of the Gospels of Matthew, Mark, and John into Roviana; and a number of others whose names can be found in the list of the pictures.
The black-and-white photographs, emulsion-paper prints, typically measure 6x8 inches in size. Several photographs are dated 1906, but most are undated. The buildings and headquarters of the company appear well developed. That suggests that 1906 is too early a date, since Mr. Meek's initial visit to the Solomons was in 1905. Most of the pictures probably date some years after 1906, but before 1914 when Commissioner Woodford left the islands. Other factors suggest that the dates range from 1906 to 1910.
Subject Headings
Leverhulme, William Hesketh Lever, Viscount, 1851-1925; Lever Brothers Company; Coconut industry; Coconut palm -- Economic aspects; Solomon Islands -- Commerce; Solomon Islands -- History -- 20th century; Solomon Islands -- Pictorial works; Solomon Islands -- Social life and customs; Black-and-white photographs; Photograph albums
Contents of Collection
- Solomon Island photograph album, 1906-1910, (1 box)
  Titles are taken from the original captions in the album.
  - Rendova Station and Bungalow. LPP, Ltd. Headquarters in the Western Solomons (Box 1)
  - Rendova labor staff (Box 1)
  - Rendova, young coconut plantations - NW (Box 1)
  - Rendova, young coconut plantations - SW (Box 1)
  - Rendova, water frontage (Box 1)
  - Rendova Island contour, clearing to left (Box 1)
  - West Bay, 2 year old plantation, Messrs. Meek, Wernham, and Kissling (Box 1)
  - West Bay, specimen of tree trunk, Messrs. Meek, Wernham, and Kissling (Box 1)
  - West Bay, system of felling trees, (2 photos) (Box 1)
  - West Bay, new clearing (Box 1)
  - Pepesala wharf, Mrs. Tillotson, Mssrs. Meek and Wernham (Box 1)
  - Erickson's Island (near Pepesala), building native houses (Box 1)
  - Collecting timber for shipment (Box 1)
  - Pepesala, bullocks drawing timber, (2 photos) (Box 1)
  - Chief Santa Auua, original owner of West Bay Estate (Box 1)
  - Sulakava, Guadalcanal bush chief, with headman and interpreter (Box 1)
  - Effects of weevil pest on young coconut trees (Box 1)
  - Kaylan plantations (Box 1)
  - Kaylan (Box 1)
  - Ufa, boats landing (Box 1)
  - Ufa plantations (Box 1)
  - Ufa plantations typical tree (Box 1)
  - Banika plantation, burning off in the distance (Box 1)
  - Banika, native quarters, (2 photos) (Box 1)
  - Banika estate, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Banika 2 year old plantations (Box 1)
  - Banika, tree planted 1906 July (Box 1)
  - Banika, typical laborers, Mr. Manchip in background (Box 1)
  - Banika household staff, Mr. Manchip in background (Box 1)
  - Opposite Banika, 8 year old trees on Capt. Butchard's property (Box 1)
  - Opposite Banika, native grove of trees on Pope's estate (Box 1)
  - Tulagi, government house, Schooner Lahloo in foreground (Box 1)
  - Gavatu, headquarters of Levers' Pacific Plantations (Box 1)
  - Gavatu company wharf (Box 1)
  - Gavatu native traders (Box 1)
  - Gavatu harbor, the Malekula (Box 1)
  - Gavatu wharf, S.S. Upolu (Box 1)
  - Lunga, Mr. Woodford on horseback in grasslands (Box 1)
  - Lunga, steam plow working, Mr. Woodford on horseback (Box 1)
  - Lunga, steam plow working, (2 photos) (Box 1)
  - Lunga, natives plowing (Box 1)
  - Lunga, plot of nuts surrounding young coconut trees (Box 1)
  - Lunga, Hevea rubber and sweet potatoes, Mr. Klotz on horseback (Box 1)
  - Lunga stables (Box 1)
  - Lunga, master's bungalow, (2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lunga, Coprah dryer (Box 1)
  - Mr. Wernham showing specimen of ground nuts (Box 1)
  - Kokoon bungalow (Box 1)
  - Kokoon plantation showing roots of can grass plowed up (Box 1)
  - Kokoon plantation from bungalow, looking towards hill (Box 1)
  - Kokoon plantation from bungalow, looking towards Lunga (Box 1)
  - Bamboo bridge connecting Kokoon with Lunga (Box 1)
  - Lunga, river (Box 1)
  - Pampa, bungalow looking west (Box 1)
  - Pampa clearing looking west (Box 1)
  - Pampa clearing, looking towards hill (Box 1)
  - Kau-Kau bungalow (Box 1)
  - Mr. Klotz (left) and his assistant ad Kau-Kau (Box 1)
  - Kaukau clearing, (4 photos) (Box 1)
  - West Bay, Chinese tallow tree (Box 1)
  - Lunga, Mrs. Woodford and Mrs. Tillotson in buggy (Box 1)
  - Lunga, Mrs. Woodford and Mrs. Tillotson in buggy with Mr. Meek, Mr. Woodford on horseback and Mr. Wernham holding horse's head (Box 1)
  - Afternoon tea on the Upolu, Mr. and Mrs. Woodford in center, Mr. Meek and Mrs. Tillotson on right (Box 1)
  - Captain and officers of the Upolu (Box 1)
  - Lunga, native girls and women (Box 1)
  - Soloman Island boy with sunshade, selling cockatoos (Box 1)
  - Aola plantation, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Capt. Erickson's schooner (Box 1)
  - Capt. Newgrien in an ordinary tracking cutter (Box 1)
  - Native war canoe (Box 1)
  - Pepesala, landing a bullock (Box 1)
  - Redowva trading station, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Rendova shipping coprah (Box 1)
  - Method of embarkation, through the surf (Box 1)
  - Mr. Woodford and hornbill bird (Box 1)
  - Stanmore River, Mr. Wernham, Mr. Barron (Chief Officer of S.S. Upolu) and Mr. Meek (Box 1)
  - Typical deck scene of outward bound island steamer (Box 1)
  - Mr. Barron (C.O. Upolu), Mr. Wernham, Mr. F. Goldie (Missionary), and 3rd engineer of Upolu (Box 1)
  - Banika, natives weeding with mattocks (Box 1)
  - Kau-Kau, traders' whaleboat (Box 1)
  - Gizo feast house (Box 1)
  - Morning Tub (Box 1)